Finding aid for George A. Malcolm papers, 1896-1965
Bentley Historical Library
George A. Malcolm papers
1896-1965
Bentley Historical Library
Malcolm, George A. (George Arthur), 1881-1961
851764 Aa 2; Ac
11 linear feet
1 oversize folder
5 digital audio files
Justice on the Philippine Supreme Court, founder of the Law School of the University of the Philippines, and attorney general of Puerto Rico. Correspondence, scrapbooks, printed reports, articles, and legal opinions, diplomas, citations, memorabilia, manuscript of book, 1956, entitled, "Sunset of Colonialism: memoirs of an American Colonial Careerist": decisions, 1909-1939, made while a jurist in the Philippines; copies of addresses and legal articles; and photographs.
The collection was received from the Malcolm family (donor no. 3955 ), 1962-1966.
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
Digitization: A number of recordings within this collection have been digitized. The resulting files are available for playback online or in the Bentley Library Reading Room according to rights. Original media are only available for staff use.
Select recordings within this collection have been digitized. Original sound recordings are only available for staff use.
George Arthur Malcolm was born November 5, 1881 in Concord, Michigan. He graduated from the Law School of the University of Michigan in 1906, then worked his way to the Philippines where he found employment as a temporary clerk in the Bureau of Health. In 1907, he transferred to the Executive Bureau as a clerk, then in 1908 again transferred to the Bureau of Justice as a law clerk. Here he was promoted to assistant attorney, and then assistant attorney general. In 1912, he came to the University of the Philippines where he founded and became dean of the College of Law. In 1917, he was appointed by President Woodrow Wilson to Associate Justice of the Supreme Court of the Philippines. He remained on the court as associate justice and presiding justice until the inauguration of the Commonwealth of the Philippines in 1935. In January 1936, he was appointed by President Franklin Roosevelt to be assistant legal adviser to United States High Commissioner Frank Murphy and later to Murphy's successor Paul V. McNutt. In September 1939, Roosevelt appointed Malcolm to be Attorney General of Puerto Rico. He took office in 1940 and served until 1942. For the remainder of his life, Malcolm would author several books, travel widely, and become a ready speaker before various groups. He died in May 16, 1961.
The Malcolm papers have been arranged into the following series: Personal and biographical; Scrapbooks; Philippine Supreme Court; Assistant Legal Adviser to United States High Commissioner; Puerto Rico Attorney General; Occasional addresses and articles: Historical topics, Philippines; Sound recordings; Visual Material; and Realia.
Judges -- Philippines.; Law.; Lawyers -- Philippines.; Philippines -- History -- 1898-1946.; Puerto Rico.; Sunset of colonialism.; Capitols -- Michigan -- Lansing.; Colonists.; Judges -- Philippines.; Philippines -- History -- 1898-1946.; Philippines -- History -- 1946-1986.; Motion pictures.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Sound recordings.; University of the Philippines.; Aguinaldo, Emilio, 1869-1964.; Ann Arbor High School (Mich.); Frankfurter, Felix, 1882-1965.; Malcolm, George A. (George Arthur), 1881-1961.; Murphy, Frank, 1890-1949.; University of the Philippines.
- Personal and biographical
  - Biographical materials, circa 1961 (Box 1)
  - Manuscript of "Sunset of Colonialism", 1956 (Box 1)
    (draft of Malcolm's published memoirs American Colonial Careerist)
  - Correspondence, 1896-1961; 10 folders (Box 1)
  - Letters addressed to Mrs. Malcolm
    - Letters of condolence, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - May-December 1961 (Box 1)
    - 1962-1965 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, Undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellanea (Box 1)
  - Diplomas and citations, 1 oversize folder (Folder 1)
  - Clippings (Box 2)
    (unprocessed in box)
- Scrapbooks
  - 1882-1906 (Box 2)
    (vol. no. 1)
  - 1906-1917 (Box 2)
    (vol. no. 2)
  - 1909-1917 (Box 2)
    (vol. no. 3)
  - 1926-1935 (Box 3)
    (vol. no. 4)
  - 1935-1939 (Box 3)
    (vol. no. 5)
  - 1939-1943 (Box 3)
    (vol. no. 6)
  - 1941-1942 (Box 3)
    (vol. no. 7-A)
  - 1942-1944 (Box 3)
    (vol. no. 7-B)
  - 1939-1940 (Box 4)
    (in Spanish; vol. no. 8)
  - 1940 (Box 4)
    (in Spanish; vol. no. 99)
  - 1940-1941, 1952 (Spanish), 1940-1952 (Box 4)
    (in Spanish; vol. no. 10)
  - 1943-1945 (Box 4)
    (vol. no. 11)
  - 1949-1953 (Box 4)
    (vol. no. 12)
  - 1949-1951 (Box 4)
    (vol. no. 13-A)
  - 1955 (Box 4)
    (vol. no. 13-B)
  - 1960-1961 (Box 4)
    (vol. no. 14)
  - Containing book reviews, 1949-1952 (Box 4)
    (vol. no. 15)
  - Containing book reviews, 1957-1958 (Box 4)
    (vol. no. 16)
- Philippine Supreme Court
  (microfilm copy available)
  - Opinions
    - 1909 (Box 5)
    - 1910 (Box 5)
    - 1911-1912 (Box 5)
    - 1913 (Box 5)
  - Decisions
    - 1917-1918 (Box 5)
    - 1918-1919 (Box 5)
    - 1919-1920 (Box 6)
    - 1920-1921 (Box 6)
    - 1921-1922 (Box 6)
    - 1922-1923 (Box 6)
    - 1923-1924 (Box 6)
    - 1924-1925 (Box 7)
    - 1925-1926 (Box 7)
    - 1926-1927 (Box 7)
    - 1927-1928 (Box 7)
    - 1928-1929 (Box 7)
    - 1929-1930 (Box 8)
    - 1930-1931 (Box 8)
    - 1931-1932 (Box 8)
    - 1933-1934 (Box 8)
    - 1934-1935 (Box 9)
  - Decisions and addresses, 1935-1936 (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous articles, addresses, etc. (Box 9)
- Assistant Legal Adviser to United States High Commissioner
  - Opinions and addresses, January 1936-November 1939 (Box 9)
- Puerto Rico Attorney General
  - Opinions of the Attorney General, 1938-1942; 2 volumes (Box 10)
  - Reports of the Attorney General, Congressional hearings and reports, and miscellaneous printed, 2 folders (Box 10)
- Occasional addresses and articles: Historical topics, Philippines
  - circa 1901-1914, 1 volume (Box 10)
  - circa 1917-1923, 1 volume (Box 10)
  - circa 1923-1929, 1 volume (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 10)
- Sound recordings, reel-to-reel tapes
  - Speech at the College of Law, University of the Philippines, December 3, 1960; [851764-SR-1]; 1 audiotape (Audiotapes, 7 1/2 ips; 7 inch) (Box 11)
    - [Side 1; no Side 2], December 3, 1960; [851764-SR-1-1]; (Discipline of Speech and Drama - University of the Philippines DZUP.)
      [Access to this material is restricted to the reading room of the Bentley Historical Library.]
      (Duration: 00:23:15)
  - Memorial service for George A. Malcolm, July 14, 1961; [851764-SR-2]; 1 audiotape (Audiotapes; 7 inch) (Box 11)
    - [Side 1], July 14, 1961; [851764-SR-2-1]; (Recording of the Memorial service for George A. Malcolm, founder of the College of Law, at the Law Theater. Recorded by Discipline of Speech and Drama College of Arts and Sciences Univeristy of the Philippines DZUP.)
      (Duration: 01:02:35)
    - [Side 2], July 14, 1961; [851764-SR-2-2]; (Choral musical performance.)
      (Duration: 00:05:01)
  - Dedication ceremonies of Malcolm Hall, University of the Philippines, November 27, 1962; [851764-SR-3]; 1 audiotape (Audiotapes; 7 inch) (Box 11)
    - [Side 1], November 27, 1962; [851764-SR-3-1]; (The dedication ceremonies for Malcolm Hall at the University of the Philipines. Unexpected content at 00:43:41 including a reading of To Juan at the Winters Solstice among others.)
      (Duration: 00:48:23)
    - [Side 2], November 27, 1962; [851764-SR-3-2]; (Unexpected content: poetry readings including The Wasteland by T.S. Eliot)
      (Duration: 00:48:24)
- Visual Material
  - Photographs
    - Portraits and informal photographs of GAM (also photographs of GAM portrait) (Box 11)
    - Family photographs; include photographs of GAM's mother in the Philippines, circa 1910 (Box 11)
    - Ann Arbor High School class picture; University of Michigan law school and alumni activities (Box 11)
    - GAM in the Michigan State Capitol building, ca. 1900. (Box 11)
    - GAM trip to Egypt, Germany, and France (Box 11)
    - GAM and Lucille Malcolm (Box 11)
    - Lucille Malcolm (alone and with various dignitaries) (Box 11)
    - GAM with Felix Frankfurter (Box 11)
    - Inauguration of the Commonwealth of the Philippines (Box 11)
      (also photographs of GAM with Frank Murphy)
    - Philippine Supreme Court (Box 11)
    - University of the Philippines: faculty, students, etc. (Box 11)
    - Dinners, awards, groups, 4 folders (Box 11)
    - Malcolm Square Memorial (Box 11)
    - Autographed photographs of various dignitaries (Box 11)
    - Manuel Roxas photographs (Box 11)
    - William H. Taft photographs (Box 11)
    - Postcards (Box 11)
  - Motion picture: Presentation of microfilm to National Library of the Philippines, 1970; 16 mm; b&w, silent, ca. 2 min. (Box 11)
- Realia
  - Items presented to Malcolm for his work in the Philippines and Puerto Rico (Box 11)
    (include medals, ribbons, salt and pepper shaker set)